hello I'm your host David Barnard and
with me today Revenue cat CEO Jacob
iding on the podcast we talk about
Revenue cats 2024 state of subscription
apps report the state of the app
industry more broadly and why a slight
drop in renewals in 20123 isn't as bad
as it might seem hey Jacob ready to talk
ciles medians and lots and lots of
numbers today I am now you didn't tell
me we're to talk ciles and medians today
Davis my favorite subject especially as
it pertains to applications on phones so
let's go so we're about to release the
2024 state of subscription apps report
and as is now the tradition year two you
and I just you and I get to go with the
numbers together this what it takes for
us to get some one-on-one time David we
have to release an entire state of
subscription apps report I've gotten
muscled off of this podcast for all the
great guests but I'll take what I can
get so I'm excited to talk today I try
and get you on with the guests that I
think would be most interesting for you
to I appreciate that I apprciate that
all right so in the first few slides of
the stateus subscription apps report
there is a great letter from the CEO
that you wrote and I thought it was so
good I actually wanted to kick off the
podcast with this because I do think
it's important before we dive into the
numbers to talk about the meta around
subscription apps and if I were to sum
it up the state of subscription apps in
2024 is good great you're going well
least yeah the first thing you talked
about was that we have been through a
tumultuous few years yeah I mean if you
just think about it Revenue cat's been
really doing our thing since 2018 2019
and if you cast backwards to that world
to where we are now a lot has happened
in just about every Dimension the
pandemic changed placement of our
businesses overnight and some of that
has reverted but not everything has
reverted I don't think we've gone back
to the way it was certainly from an
industry's perspective the apps just
became much more important it changed
consumer Behavior forever but then also
it created this immense monetary bubble
during 2020 and 2021 that had
aftershocks that lasted clear through
2022 and if anything we talk about why I
think 2023 was a better year is that 23
year was the first year we were kind of
clear of most of that it was still a
little bit happening the beginning of
2023 but really felt like the first year
that things had sort of resettled and
renormalized and then alongside that
we've had all kinds of crazy side shows
that have gone on there's been all this
antitrust stuff with Apple and Google as
well as like their regulatory issues in
different countries and app tracking
transparency yeah and then that was the
other one I was going to mention like
apple basically turned on its head going
acquisition strategy for apps in that
time period so yeah a lot of that stuff
all kind of happened between 2019 and
2022 so by 2023 I think we were really
finally set up to kind of have a quote
unquote normal year for apps if anything
I think we learned is that apps are
still here they're still growing we have
a different set of sort of winners in
2023 as you will and like a a very
Dynamic Market but yeah and if anything
it's got me more bullish for this whole
industry because yeah we can kind of
survive figure it out we can renormalize
and you know in some cases we accelerate
I'll say from our business we certainly
have benefited in the last year from
customers growing but as well as maybe
some new trends and then also just the
relative stability of the global
macroeconomic condition which bitcoin's
up 25% in the last 30 days as we're
recording this which doesn't tend
anything positive so maybe this is very
untimely by the time this is released
but so far so good into the first couple
months of 2024 one of the things that
does excite me about how strong 2023 was
is that it wasn't until the louder part
of 2023 that I started hearing from a
lot of people in Industry that the app
tracking transparency stuff had started
to renormalize like meta is finally
finding its footing really toward the
end of 2023 and that was such a huge
driver of growth for Ops as being able
to buy everybody blames The Meta
collapse and rebirth on zuck's over
focus on like the metaverse and things
like this but I think probably as much
if not most of it can be attributed to
at right yeah yeah and so I'm excited
coming into 2024 that it has been
getting easier and easier like it was
preat to find those users who are going
to be profitable and so I think that's
kind of what we're seeing like you said
it's like apps in 2023 were thriving and
I think it wasn't just like
year-over-year that 202 2 was an easy
beat seem to have a good year when
you're lapping a bad year right yeah but
I do feel like there's wind in the sales
again for the first time in a few years
with things being better the other thing
I wanted to bring up before we kind of
move on to some of the other things you
mentioned and you didn't mention this
specifically in your opening letter but
it's something I think about a ton I
feel like I'm always seeing articles
like subscription fatigue too many
things are subscription and people are
annoyed and how many more streaming
services can you subscribe to but it's
like we don't see that in our data
anyway no I mean we don't have great
share of spend per customer which
actually may be something we could start
to compute over time but I've always
felt like subscription fatigue was just
a convenient angle that was popular for
clicks the economics of it never really
shook out if anything apps and software
have driven down the costs of the
services they provide in the last decade
and we were just talking before the call
about streaming services as a specific
example and sort of unbundling of cable
in my head I was like God Cable's $100 a
month right but if think about it that
was $100 a month in 2008 right which is
like a lot more today and I don't spend
$100 a month on Hulu and Prime and
whatever other streaming services I have
that allow me to stay unbundled from
cable and they're so much better things
are probably going to change post zerp
post zero interest times and studios are
starting to cut back but if you think
about the last few years we've had kind
of the golden age of TV and movies
struggled because of covid and box
office but we're paying less then
especially inflation adjusted we ever
did for cable we're not seeing ads we're
getting like the best content that's
ever been created in human history I
mean there's like tons of shows that I
hear people talk about that I don't even
have time to watch so it's like there's
so much great stuff and I think that's
kind of reflective more broadly of the
subscription app industry is that
developers are creating just so much
value and creating more and more and
more value and then that value is being
captured in price I don't see why you
couldn't take that analogy from
streaming services cable to streaming
services to kind of every other domain
of mobile apps right you mentioned
there's been some readjusting on the
media company ecosystem there's been a
lot of layoffs and things like this and
potentially you know we're going to see
less content being created but at the
same time we have this Rising trend of
generative AI tools I'm not a person who
believes that you're going to type in
and get your own custom movie in my
lifetime or maybe in my lifetime but I
don't think that something is around the
corner but I do think that every
creative professional whether they like
it or not are going to be using AI tools
for leverages whether that's in VFX or
script writing or whatever which is
further going to drive down the cost of
producing content in media further going
to increase the amount that you can get
for the same dollar I talked about AI in
the report even though it kind of felt
like industry buzzwordy just to be
shoving AI in there but we got to talk
about it because llms I feel like open
AI kind of really had their breakout
year they released Chad gbt 3.5 the end
of 2022 and then it really hit
Commercial Appeal their app came out
this year we also saw the of Google's
attempts and like everybody else is
getting their AI products out and I
think what surprised me was that how
much of a consumer Revolution it was
like I kind of always assumed that this
was going to be for back office stuff
and models and things like this but
turns out that a well-trained decent llm
in your pocket is a pretty powerful tool
that most people can get it became a
consumer brand and not just chat gbt I
mean consumers started using generative
AI very very quickly and we've also seen
AI get incorporated into app and so
there's been takes on the internet which
I don't think are wrong that potentially
we're at the end of the mobile S curve
right so if you can think about the
transition to mobile that really has
driven growth in technology I think at
least on the consumer side for the last
decade started in what 2008 2009
something like that 2013 2014 that's
when Peak adoption was happening it was
like the abss were ripping and there's
no end in sight and then maybe around
2017 2018 we started to see the backside
of more people had smartphones than
didn't and things like this and that's
LED some people to the conclusion that
like the mobile Revolution is over right
and it's like yeah probably like we've
reached saturation there um Hardware in
Hardware right and maybe the first Beach
head of consumer behaviors but like
think about the PC right like you could
have drawn that adoption curve in the
90s for the PC or the internet but then
if you actually map that to the value
that was going to be generated by those
Technologies those were purely
exponential because every continuing
advancement was built on top of those
Technologies and used those Technologies
so it wasn't purely replacing it now
there may be a day and I constantly
trying to like see if I can see around
the corner here and predict will we see
a fall of the mobile device in the App
Store as it is and like I'll say that
certainly in this year has given me more
reason to pause and think about like the
future of developers and apps and things
like this when a computer can do a lot
of it that it couldn't 18 months ago I
won't say I know the future I just think
it's gonna be interesting and there may
be a future disruptive event for mobile
but I really believe that the immediate
value of these AI apps especially for
consumers I won't name names but every
time I'd see a big breakout app on the
revenue cat internal dashboards and
stuff this year it was almost always
something AI like either a generative AI
or an application of AI or adding llms
to an existing use case and so I really
think these Technologies are going to be
linked just like the internet and Web
2.0 and social were just like social and
mobile were as well like these
Technologies kind of have interlocking
behaviors so maybe I'm wrong and maybe
this is just coat but I don't think the
mobile Revolution is over so everybody
can keep subscribing to the podcast keep
investing keep downloading X code I
think it's going to to pay off so I
think it's worth pointing out and Diving
a little deeper on how the scurve of
adoption does not necessarily parallel
any way you would chart value derived
from that hardware and so for example
like dishwasher adoption like when you
see these historic adoption curves of
new technology it's like once you've
adopted a dishwasher the kind of value
in your life is fairly set I mean for me
I had more kids the more kids you have
maybe the value goes up slightly but
basically it's like car adoption you
know electricity adoption and so much of
like historic adoption of new technology
there's kind of a cap on the amount of
value you derive from it in your life
like you adopt a car it's like you get
my 2023 Tesla is nicer than my 95
cutless supreme but it's not
transformatively different in how it
changes my life you know what I mean
yeah but then PC adoption to your point
and then now smartphone adoption it's
like we reached close enough to Peak the
s-curve adoption decades ago for PC or
not quite decades but both Technologies
are very mature at this point but the
value that you get from those
Technologies has continued to increase
like you said exponentially yeah it's
cuz you're adding a bunch of s-curves
together the true like acceleration
curve of Technology over time is the
summation of many many different S
curves let's called a logistic curve
added together and if you add them all
together and you zoom out oh wow it's
exponential but any one technology is
going to have its impact and you know
don't know where we draw the lines on
like what is a technology versus nons
you know when is a phone not a computer
and when is a VR headset not a phone and
all those things it's kind of arbitrary
you know when you know like I think llms
are a new curve that that is certainly I
don't think anybody's going to debate
that interacting with a talking computer
is is not something novel and different
and has actually utility but maybe
people get a little too excited to say
like Doom say about the end of
Technologies and others which certainly
happens right like it's not unheard of
for one technology to be disrupted by
another and that's why I said in terms
of ai's application to mobile like there
will be winners people will adopt it and
win others will miss the boat and their
products will be outdated but it's not
necessarily a wholesale replacement and
so it just got to be on your toes figure
out how to integrate this stuff and and
where are we experiencing the value
derived from AI primarily on our devices
yeah it's the mode of consumption right
and for our customers it's dual because
it's and this is maybe a little bit too
behind the scenes but it's the value it
can provide to our customers and user
experience Revenue cat doesn't use a ton
of AI in the product necessarily but
like internally we use it a ton right
like every developer we have is using
co-pilot it has changed the way we can
build stuff and how fast we can build
stuff and I'm sure you don't need to be
convinced to use technology that is
useful so I don't have to here and chill
like people will just use it if it is it
just felt like the AI narrative and
story this year is something we'll kind
of remember as a transformative year and
it certainly has an impact on our
industry so I felt like it was worth
mentioning I think a good summary of the
2024 report and we'll point out a few
areas that did lag in 2023 compared to
2022 but it was just bigger stronger
faster better A lot of good stuff
happening yeah we can get into the
report in terms of how we structured it
this time we're throwing stuff at the
wall here we just tried more charts
twice as many charts if you add up the
number of additional segments we added
in data points it's probably way more
than two times the amount of data it's
probably four or five times the amount
of data we'll see what the customer
feedback is and see how people like and
what they don't like but we've certainly
enhanced our ability to process this
data in the last year we went deeper and
broader in a lot of areas with the same
sort of mission as the first report
which is to give you some real numbers
you can kind of stick to when you're
making decisions about strategy about
pricing strategy or localization
strategy I would say largely around go
to market strategy for your apps but we
tried to cover a pretty spanning set of
data that will be interesting for you as
you're making some educated guesses I
like how you ended it stop guessing
start acting what do you think is the
best use of benchmarks for a company in
the space like when you see these trial
startart rates when you see the download
to paid conversion rate when you see
these numbers in the 2024 report like
how does the average consumer
subscription app look at these numbers
and make better decisions based on it
yeah I mean I think any given day as a
business owner you're trying to just
move the needle you're trying to grow
your Revenue you're trying to make your
app stickier you're trying to find
better product Market fit which there's
two sides of that there's the product
and the market I would say this report
leans on the market side of that it's
like what parts of the market and
pricing and things like that are
relevant the way I always use benchmarks
just a rough idea how's our trial
conversion rate look is it in the median
is it high is it low you know you
shouldn't be working on the things that
you're good at really you should
probably be working on the things that
you can stand to improve what's most
important is to contextualize all the
things you look at into your app like
what are you doing that might be driving
this number down compared to like 10 of
your peers right and I think that's
really important for every person
consuming this data to do because if you
just look at it and go like we should
have x% trial conversion rate and it's
like well maybe is your trial really
expensive is it really short is your
product experimental like there's going
to be things that affect that none of
this data you should be able to just
take and put it as your okay RS for the
year or whatever right I think you need
to take it in and contextualize it but
it should give you notional orders of
magnitude ideas of like where to focus
your time and energy and what
experiments are worth trying because
ultimately I think you should use this
to drive experiments and try things you
shouldn't use this as like the ground
truth because every app is different the
variance can be very high Within These
parameters so everybody's got to try it
but I think having rough numbers can be
a starting point for a discussion on
what we should try rather than an answer
yeah one of the things I really do like
about the extra data we put in this year
and we'll talk about this in a few
specific cases as we dig into the data
but because we broke it down by country
and broke it down by category like if
your business that's looking to expand
your portfolio of apps well you can look
at the categories and see which
categories are doing well if you're
primarily us focused and you're thinking
where do I localize first you can look
at how different countries monetize
there are a lot of places in the data to
find opportunity this year yeah and even
if you don't have an app yet it's also
great if you're thinking about starting
an app you know for instance I think one
of our first data points is download to
paid in South Korea for Education apps
is over 10% which would probably be like
top desile like you knew that right so
right maybe that's a good idea starting
with some Tailwinds that's another thing
is like find your Tailwinds find the
places you can go where it will be easy
for you to succeed and don't waste time
I see a lot of developers especially
with localization is a really good one
like developers will go super Broad and
localize everywhere and bl or like focus
on conversion in certain countries where
it's just like you're never going to
turn a dime focusing on conversion in
that country like don't worry about it
at your scale and I think this can be as
much as a negative guide of where not to
focus as it is where to focus right yeah
and we'll get into it but it is
interesting how the data confirms a lot
of the biases in the industry like North
America average realized LTV is just way
higher than other countries and Maps
pretty well to like price purchasing
parody GDP per capita pretty well and it
just Maps broadly to so many apps being
more North American focused and those
specific markets that do get a lot of
focus like there's a reason people focus
on the US as their primary market for
apps is that it has the highest realiz
LTV so anyways let's start with the five
key takeaways and since those were the
highlights of the report in the report
itself I figured that would be the place
to kind of dive in and talk through it
so I'll just read them and then we can
talk through the implications and what
it means and all that so the first key
takeaway is that
1.7% of downloads turned into paying
subscribers in the first 30 days which
is slightly up from last report the
difference between lower quartile which
is 0.6% and the upper quartile which is
4.2% remains striking a 7x spread right
that's not even like top desile lowest
desile right that's cortile so the top
25% of apps is seven times plus more
than the bottom 25 which is interesting
but that median about 1.7 I think is
that's always a number I've used in my
head is like how many people are going
to convert to paid in an app it's a few
percentage points usually if you're
lucky maybe you can get close to five I
think generally true so I'm glad we LED
with this in the report as like the
biggest takeaway because ultimately I
don't think all subscription businesses
need to convert more users a lot are
premium and they have more generous
premium tier maybe they monetize via ads
maybe they have a Marketplace or other
monetization layered in and that's
another Trend we didn't I don't think
talked about much in the report but this
kind of hybrid monetization is something
that's definitely I think we talked
about a little bit last year and
definitely been talking about it in
other episodes of the sub Club podcast
but
1.7% median turning people into paid
subscrib like this it's such a numbers
game 98 users who never pay for every
two that do from download I think the
scale of it sometimes especially people
who don't do this work day in day out
don't realize certainly users don't
understand the economics that 98% of
people who download your app aren't
going to give you a dime they're not
useless but they're not going to
monetize probably yeah a couple other
things I thought interesting to point
out is that in this chart and again it
always sucks like trying to do a podcast
about charts yeah it's great everybody
loves it and I guess we didn't mention
this at the start but go to Revue
cat.com report to follow along so pause
your podcast download the report and
then go to the download to paid chart
and what you'll see is yellow is North
America and pretty much in every
category North America download to paid
is just way higher than any other
country in the world except for as Jacob
pointed
out interesting that in travel and
education and a few other categories
there are some standouts in other
geographies but generally it is a very
kind of North America Focus that on
average a North American user is way
more likely to become a subscriber to
your app than pretty much any other
country in the world what's interesting
to me that because this is a rate right
it's a percentage the fact that the US
is so much a higher percentage tells me
that probably not enough people are
doing Regional price discrimination
because ideally you would probably want
to lower your price in those countries
you'll lower your price but you'll raise
your conversion rate and you could
potentially like reach your max value
curve assuming your North American rates
are on par but like if people were
perfectly efficiently pricing you would
think that for a given distribution of
consumers like the same percentage of
them would be buying if the price were
set at like an optimal Point again all
these things are really tricky because
you have many many dimensions of things
that interplay yeah and I would say the
counterargument to that and this is
something I don't have data on but I've
talked to several developers who think
this and who look at their data and
think this to be true in a lot of
countries you end up converting the kind
of middle class and upper middle class
who aren't as price sensitive as the
average consumer in that country and so
if you do drop your prices you're just
lowering what those middle class and
upper middle class people end up paying
you versus actually extending the price
low enough to where the kind of average
consumer in that country something you
should test if you can r.com experiments
I don't know if that works but there's
experiments on our website but that is
something you could test and run because
yeah you might be right again it's like
you're dealing with so many nonlinear
distributions of things it's really
difficult to know without real
experimentation I think both points are
valid like for some apps it's going to
be the case that the monetization is not
going to improve with regional pricing
but for some apps it actually will could
yeah just depends on where you're
sitting on the value maximization curve
exactly all right the next top takeaway
is that the top 5% of newly launched
apps generate over 200 times more
monthly Revenue than the bottom cor
child does one year after launch I'm not
sure why we we feel like shoving
everybody's NOS in this one uh kind of
sucks I'm sure there's some listeners in
that top 5% but the rest of us just like
what what the heck this is just a
natural side effect of the way that
power laws work in the world right where
each order of magnitude and revenue you
go up that you go down and Order
magnitude and number of actors
generating that Revenue in most business
and competitive markets and so it's
interesting I don't know if it
necessarily is actionable my advice
become one of those top five% that's my
advice I don't have the data here but
there's a lot of meat in that long tail
so you think about who's in that top 5%
it's Netflix maybe not So Much Anymore
but it's like the top brands I mean HBO
Max I know does in out purchases they're
probably one of the top ones Disney plus
is very in on out purchases Fortune 100
brands are going to dominate just
because of their brand awareness and
mass consumer appeal so don't get too
demoralized by that because there's lots
of riches and niches like all the way
down the curve so yeah and just to be
clear for listeners all of this data is
actually Revenue cat data only and those
big streaming companies are not yet
Revenue cat customers so we don't have
their data in the mix but broadly
looking at the subscription app category
to far away interesting the most Revenue
with power laws no matter how you slice
it it's going to be true right like
power all the way up I do think it's
encouraging also though like if you're
an indie developer and you just got your
app out there and you look at these
numbers you're doing something you're
making some money and a lot of these are
going to be side projects and nice and
weekends and stuff like that and so it's
cool to see how many apps do make some
amount of money though and we see this
all the time it's really fun inside
Revenue cat weird software people make
yeah yeah people tweet out hey I just
got my first subscriber hey I just
crossed like $100 in monthly track
revenue and for like a night and weekend
project that you're just throwing out
there into the world it's pretty cool
that you can build something that like
people fre kind of right hobby money at
least there's one breakdown in this
piece of data that's interesting which
is that the median revenue for new app
after a year is $50 which like should be
a little upsetting but basically like
half of apps launched a year later make
almost no money which probably surprises
a lot of people right and I think this
shouldn't be discouraging it just
highlights that while most apps don't
work out or most people don't put enough
effort in to make them work out or
they're just not interested or it's just
like a side project or it's whatever
it's a thing it doesn't take a ton of
effort to get you into that second half
and the numbers go up rapidly after that
point which is interesting right like so
we have some data here it's roughly 50
for the median but if you just get into
that upper cortile it jumps by almost a
factor of 10 to like 3 or 400 and then
once you're in that upper cortile then
when it starts to go up really
precipitously again because of power law
effects it's like the winners will
continue to be winners and most people
when they have an app that doesn't
really take off a lot of times they
divest naturally right which is good I
mean that's a sign of a dynamic and
efficient market that people are not
focusing too much on the ones that
aren't breaking out and they're doubling
down and growing the ones that do break
out and this is what you see a ton in
like the Indie hacker space and stuff
say you you just keep building until it
makes level IO guy yeah yeah he was just
talking about today his takeaway after
all these years is that no matter how
good he gets the probability that
something works out for him is still
pretty random the only bet is to like
keep trying stuff until something really
works and so that would be my takeaway
from this is like don't get discouraged
because you don't feel like you ever be
in that top 5% top cortile you just got
to keep trying stuff until something
really cracks and then the way
subscription works you just double down
and you compound into that as long as
you can that's sort of the nature of
growing something really big in this
game I think the toughest part is
deciding when to double down on what
seems like it's not working and maybe
this report will help with that like if
you're in that category of you haven't
quite hit the $50 a month in Revenue
we've talked about on the podcast so
many developers who and maybe it wasn't
quite that $50 in Revenue but Curtis
Herbert made like 10 grand his first
year that's a lot more than $50 right
yeah it is that puts him in the top 5%
actually yeah but it's tough to know
like when to keep doubling down on the
existing like if you're making thousands
of dollars in your first year like
that's might be enough of a signal to
keep reinvesting if you're making tens
of dollars any app that's got any amount
of product Market fit and has any kind
of legs like if you think you released
something that was just useless or just
very very close to MVP and you only make
$50 I wouldn't take that as a valid data
point but like if you build something
pretty good you think it's really good
you invested a lot and in the first year
it's not naturally making $10,000 or
something along those lines I don't
think fixing any number in our reports
probably going to help I would suggest
if you got a different idea try
something more radical and that might be
advice generally on this like the
further you are away from the metrics
you want you should proportionately
increase the radicalness of the testing
and experimentation you try right if you
have pretty good conversion rate don't
go crazy but if you have total trash
like you're not losing anything just try
something nuts you want really high
variance like dice rolls and rrolling
and building a new app might be the
biggest experiment you could do right
yeah and some of the experiments that
need to be done though in these cas is
if you are making less than $50 a month
on your app after a year is like how are
you getting attention and figure out a
way to get more attention if you just
put it out into the world and if I build
it they will come like figure out how to
get attention that should be your final
dice roll before you give up on a
project is like really try and figure
out how can I get attention you're not
going to get traction just from
background noise on the App Store
anymore right you have to kick something
to try but do something if you do and
nothing takes off then yeah you know and
this is really hard for entrepreneurs
across the board like when is it time to
throw in the towel or roll or try
something new it's never an easy answer
because there's tons of sunk costs and
all kinds of things correct me again
David because it's $50 per month that's
the cortile it's not $50 for the whole
year it's $50 per month by their 12th
month which is marginally less bad but
all right number three of the top
takeaways the average realized LTV per
download in North America 14 days in is
four times the global average at 35
cents compared to 8 cents a multiple
that exists both on the App Store as
well as on Google Play I was just trying
to Google North American GDP per capita
versus world GDP per capita but I'm
surprised it's not actually higher than
that I guess because true rest of world
GDP per capita is not going to be
inclusive of the non-north American App
Store users there's definitely some bias
in the fact that the iPhone was a us
first invention and there's probably
some Lon share of the developers that
are here we see us is our biggest single
country I think maybe EU and aggregate
might be a close second for Revenue cat
but the US is still very dominant it's
still King yeah you know there's always
going to be things in reports like this
that I wish you could break down a
hundred more ways it would be
fascinating maybe we can do this as a
follow-up log post at some point but
take especially this key figure because
I do think this is so interesting the
average realized LTB 14 days in and then
60 days in is the chart we're looking at
and we bundle Europe as e mea which I
had to look up that acronym again today
but it's Europe Middle East Africa is
the a Africa is I think it's Europe
Middle East Africa is the there you go
Europe Middle East Africa or emia if you
will the first time you ever meet a
Management Consultant you're going to
hear the words emia and Lam and you're
going to go like what are we talking
about I don't know what these words are
it would be really fascinating to
actually like break this down country by
country this specific one because I do
think that North America and North
America again does include Canada and I
believe it depends who you talk to like
I don't know sometimes folks throw it in
sometimes they'll consider Mexico in
Latin America category but yeah I'll
make sure that we put this in the
methodology whether or not we included
Mexico or not but anyways it would be
fascinating to break this down country
by country because I think the US would
still lead far and away but I do think
certain European countries like the UK
maybe even Australia from talking to
other Vel opers on a per capita basis
there are probably other countries that
are actually closer to North America
than it looks like in the data because
we're bundling so many countries into
EMA and rest of world and whatnot I
think worth pointing out here and you
can kind of see it in a lot of the
charts here is the relative strength of
Japan and South Korea for our markets
especially relative to their size these
are non-trivial markets they tend to be
dominated by local players but they're
very close you know again Europe is 30
Country I don't know how many countries
are in Europe combined with all distinct
languages but Japan and South Korea are
monocultures more or less in those
countries and single languages and may
be worth focusing on even though they
can be difficult to break into in terms
of like if you're looking for secondary
markets and I think like we're talking
about this at Revenue cat right now
which is like starting to look at our
local specific strategies as a SAS
business and I think for Consumer it's
even more important to be strategic
about where you focus because it can
have a good upside but it's also comes
with like substantial costs and so you
don't want to go localizing for you know
I don't want to throw any country under
the bus being like small and not worth
it but like there are some that are
going to get you a better return on
investment than others and you should be
strategic about how you deploy those
resources to the point I made earlier as
well if you look at a country like India
broadly you might think it's not worth
localizing in India but there is a
thriving middle and upper middle class
in India country right that's the other
thing the per capita might be low but
the number of people is much bigger so
big yeah so there are opportunities even
hidden in some of these averages that
you need to understand for your business
whether there is relevance in some of
these bigger countries that maybe on
average have lower income but might
actually do really well in your
particular case the other thing I
thought interesting to point out in this
chart is that Japan and South Korea both
actually monetize really well on the
Play Store they actually monetize better
on the Play Store in terms of realized
LTV than they do on the App Store now
some of that is South Korea is the
headquarters of Samsung and so it is a
very kind of Android and Samsung focused
country but I was actually surprised to
see that the same was true of Japan as
well yeah I mean I think there's The
Stereotype that iPhone owners are higher
payers and follow some there's some
cultural connotations that at least in
the west we have around iPhone versus
Android and things like this but you
know those are just that cultural
stereotypes they're not necessarily like
hard and fast rules and I mean even in
Europe Android is much more popular I
don't know as a spending platform but on
a day-to-day basis bis it's a much more
popular platform we all work in often
like the tech ecosystem bubble where
iPhone and iOS is dominant but it's not
the real world so yeah you have to think
about that too in terms of your
multiplatform strategy of you might want
to consider going multiplatform before
you consider a focused localization
effort just for that yeah totally and
then one of the Striking things too is
that rest of World Android just gets
crushed by iOS and I think that's maybe
that point of these are the $80 Android
headsets in third world countries that
just aren't ever going to monetize very
well at all they're not made for App
Store monetization right they're made
for a different case all right so the
fourth key takeaway is that the share of
monthly subscribers retained after 12
months dropped by 14% last year across
categories and impacting both the best
and the worst performers alike this is
the one area in the state of
subscription apps report this year that
was a soft spot was retention and since
we won't have time to kind of get to
some of the other charts I did want to
highlight deeper in the retention some
of the other softness so first renewal
rates dropped in 2023 across all
subscription durations we're talking 3%
for monthly median 133% for annual when
you say that are you talking about
relative drops or absolute values yeah
yeah sorry relative drop not an absolute
drop so it is interesting that the first
renewal rates dropped and that the Year
One retention dropped in 2023 and I
think there's a lot of potential reasons
why this is actually the case a lot of
apps were pushing Harder Faster than
ever in 2023 monetizing more
aggressively like showing their payal
more frequently bringing in maybe lower
intent users like there's so many
reasons why
ramping right as you're pushing further
into acquisition you're going to affect
these numbers and like yeah the
relatives are decently high for instance
like the annual renewal rates are down %
which is the effect you'll see on that
like amount of money you'll make but if
we talk about absolute numbers it's like
last year we measured 30 a half% first
year renewal rate this year it was 28
it's significant we see it across all
durations but it's also not necessarily
a total change in the regime of what's
workable and what's not in terms of
viable business models but it is
interesting I mean and I I also won't
hold back that there could be some bias
in our data here as like our data set
expands and Grows Right which should
proxy to the overall Market you know
Revenue cast more or less established
and mature at this point too but there
could be some of that but yeah certainly
interesting yeah and then you would
expect that like as apps grow faster as
the market grows and we talked about
this ton on the podcast too is how
monetizing more strongly and putting pay
walls earlier in the onboarding and
things like that and for it to only be a
10 to 13% relative drop to your point
it's not massive it's not groundbreaking
like description app industry is falling
apart everybody's turning I certainly
even be normalized by those remaining
80% or whatever retaining better in the
long run right so yeah it's hard to look
at any single stage gate and really
understand the overall macro impact but
the number is true for what it's worth
and I don't know how the total impact of
that the number is as we measured it
true and there probably is some bit of
macro mixed in there of you know in 2023
people were looking for things to cut
and inflation with four kids I
definitely noticed my grocy bill go up
considerably in 2022 and 20 23 and so I
probably cut a few subscriptions that I
wasn't using as aggressively a little
bit of macro too inflation soak up price
changes happened in that year so that
could even just be an explainer itself
all right the last of the five key
takeaways is that over 10% of turned
monthly subscribers resubscribe within
12 months with categories like media and
entertainment seeing even higher
reactivation rates this was interesting
and we haven't done this before so there
was no kind of year-over-year compar
but it is really encouraging another to
get back to encouraging exciting stats
is that you can win people back there
are opportunities to get those
subscribers back turn and it's a
compounding effect too versus new
acquisition right like new acquisition
you're exerting some amount of effort
for every new potential trial and sign
up and then you know retain and churn
but as you build that over time you have
the number of churned unactivated
customers grows and grows and grows and
grows and grows it never goes down and
so similarly that if you can reactivate
10% of that that 10% becomes bigger and
bigger and bigger every year and you'll
see this in very mature consumer apps
that reactivation is a huge part of
their growth model dualingo I know for
example that is a huge component of
their growth model is reactivating
dormant users I know Twitter back in the
day reactivation was always a huge
driver of their growth model I'll admit
we haven't done much here on Revenue Cat
Side to like lean into this but I think
it's something we want to do more to
help you monetize or just reactivate and
bring those users back into the fold
because they've already primed they paid
once they're very very likely to pay
again if you just give them the right
pitch to your point though it's actually
more impactful the larger you are and
the more people you've had previously
subscribed that aren't not one strategy
right yeah exactly before you think oh
man I need to go reactivate all these
subscribers and put a ton of work into
CRM and win back campaigns 15 users
turned last month let's build out
infrastructure it's like no don't worry
about them wait till there's 500 or a
thousand exactly like grow first and
then think more about reactivation
because it's going be even more powerful
than to or do just the lowest hanging
fruit the easy winds here that assumes
there's nothing else to work on right
you know you want to be very focused on
like funnel and very basic acquisition
retention stuff in the early days and
then you transition more to like
reactivation over time yep totally all
right well that was the five key
takeaways that we covered in the report
I think we have time to squeeze one more
in and this was the one I found most
striking and I think is maybe the most
actionable if you're not already doing
this you should and so the title of this
chart is that most trial starts occur
within the first 24 hours and then you
look at the chart and again I'm going to
try and describe a chart on a podcast
but blue is within the first 24 hours
and then red is one to three days yellow
is four to seven days and in pretty much
every category across the board blue is
just dominous most is an understatement
it's like the far it's like 70 plus% on
average and so this is something worth
knowing if you don't know this but yes
most of your effort should be focused on
that very first user experience getting
a trial started for two reasons one you
have the maximum user intent they just
downloaded your app this problem that
they have is acute to them at that
moment so they're very very primed and
then secondly it's just a law of numbers
like most people are not going to open
your app the second time unless you hook
them this is true for any kind of sales
like you really want to like land that
message and that pitch in that moment
because you might not have another
chance lot of seem I see people struggle
and be like Oh I'm going to let people
sign up and then they're going to set an
alert and then on four days once they've
taken some sort of action then I'm going
to hit him with the pay wall and it's
like yeah that sounds like a really
ideal experience that one fifth of the
downloads are going to see right so like
as much as you think that might be ideal
I will beat you just by putting a buy
button on the first screen by pure law
of numbers right and that's sort of the
like un aour app design things that you
sometimes need to do to actually
optimize the business this met just
really drives that home you can still do
that in tasteful ways right like you can
do that without compromising that much
but yeah this is one of those like
truths of apps that you just have to
know like you got to get that trial
started right away yeah and then again
when looking at Opportunity those 15
people who turned last month is a very
small number compared to the hundreds
who opened your app on any given day and
there's a lot of smart things you can do
here as well Jake Moore talked about
this a lot and it's something I'm
actually working to to implement my app
soon is that if they don't subscribe in
that first session hit them in that
first 24 hours like when the app is
still fresh in their mind hit them with
a discount in that first 24 hours right
their Peak intent is probably going to
be right then so just get them when you
can all right well this has been a ton
of fun Jacob we'll see you on the
podcast I'm sure I'm gonna be inv back
I'd love to I'd love to be on this
podcast but I always look forward to the
state of subscription so hopefully less
than a year from now cuz this is a
little late for us don't blow us up
David we always meant to launch it in
March you got to keep the facade up
we're perfectly on time we just wanted
to do it later than every other uh
company that does these that was the
whole plan all of course but yeah
looking forward to the 2025 report and I
think there's going to be a lot of
really fun and interesting things to
discuss then but yeah go download the
report let us know what you think let us
know how to improve it and hopefully
this report will help you make more
money thanks so much for listening if
you have a minute please leave a review
in your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to join
our private
[Music]
community